<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<chapter id ="prepare_database">
  	<title>Prepare Database</title>
  	    <para>For the moment, we will use the OSM map of Brussels. The data was fetched via the OpenStreetMap API (Overpass API) and then reduced into a zip file. The result can be found in the root of the project in the file ./brussels.zip. Please extract this file in order to get ./brussels.osm file. Then, open a console</para>
  	    <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
$ createdb -h localhost -p 5432 -U dbowner brusselsOTP
-- replace localhost with your database host, 5432 with your port,
-- and dbowner with your database use
      </programlisting>
      <para>this command line allows the creation of the brusselsOTP database that we will use throughout this workshop</para>
      <para>ConnectOTP is a project that depends on  Postgis, MobilityDB as well as Hstore. This is why we need to add these extensions to our database</para>
      <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
-- create needed extensions 
$ psql -h localhost -p 5432 -U dbowner -d brusselsOTP  -c 'CREATE EXTENSION hstore'

$ psql -h localhost -p 5432 -U dbowner -d brusselsOTP  -c 'CREATE EXTENSION postgis'
$ psql -h localhost -p 5432 -U dbowner -d brusselsOTP  -c 'CREATE EXTENSION MobilityDB '
-- adds the PostGIS and the MobilityDB extensions to the database
	    </programlisting>
	    
	    <para>The last two lines can be executed in a single line by using the <varname>CASCADE</varname> parameter which install Postgis extension  before installing MobilityDB extension .</para>
      <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
$ psql -h localhost -p 5432 -U dbowner -d brusselsOTP  -c 'CREATE EXTENSION MobilityDB CASCADE'
      </programlisting>
      
      <para>This last command will allow us to create a topology for the city of Brussels by creating two tables, namely <varname>ways</varname> as well as <varname>ways_vertices_pgr</varname></para>
     <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
$ osm2pgrouting -W 'password' -h localhost -p 5432 -U dbowner -f brussels.osm -d brusselsOTP
-- replace password by your dbowner's password
      </programlisting>
        
        <para>the table <varname>ways_vertices_pgr</varname> brings us more than 116000 nodes located in the Brussels area. It is from these points that we will choose our source nodes and target nodes.</para>
</chapter>